<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2025-10-22T16:44:08-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jonathan Fuller</title><subtitle>Evidence-driven cybersecurity leadership, research, and outreach from Jonathan Fuller.
</subtitle><author><name>Jonathan Fuller</name><email>hello@empiricaldefense.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">From Anomalous Traffic to Spycraft 2.0</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/spycraft-2-0/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Anomalous Traffic to Spycraft 2.0" /><published>2025-10-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-10-22T09:32:07-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/spycraft-2-0-bsidesnyc</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/spycraft-2-0/"><![CDATA[<p>During a reverse-engineering session, we encountered something unexpected: a malware sample opened an HTTPS session not to its known command-and-control (C&amp;C) destination, but to <strong>X.com</strong>. That single anomaly prompted a deeper question: was this an isolated artifact, or evidence of a new operational pattern we call <strong>Spycraft 2.0</strong>, where adversaries conceal command instructions within legitimate web services?</p>

<p>This observation exposed a larger issue. Malware authors increasingly rely on the open internet not only as infrastructure but as camouflage. If attackers can turn ordinary web applications into covert C&amp;C rendezvous points, defenders must learn to detect and stop them. Our research, presented at <strong>BSidesNYC 0x05</strong>, investigates how modern malware hides in plain sight and how defenders can invert that tactic to gain early visibility.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="dead-drop-resolvers-the-modern-dead-drop">Dead Drop Resolvers: The Modern Dead Drop</h2>

<p>At the core of Spycraft 2.0 is the <strong>Dead Drop Resolver (DDR)</strong>, a digital version of Cold War tradecraft. Instead of placing a physical message in a park or under a brick, malware operators encode their C&amp;C addresses and host them inside public web services such as Pastebin, X.com, GitHub, or blockchain explorers. Once executed, the malware retrieves, decodes, and reconstructs the live C&amp;C endpoint.</p>

<p>DDR techniques are effective because they blend naturally with legitimate network activity. They exhibit several key traits:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Anonymity and elasticity:</strong> each dead drop is disposable, hosted on reputable public domains that constantly change and scale.</li>
  <li><strong>Benign-looking traffic:</strong> HTTPS requests to popular platforms appear legitimate, making DDR fetches indistinguishable from normal user behavior.</li>
  <li><strong>Multi-layer manipulation:</strong> malware authors encode or encrypt data using multiple algorithms (e.g., Base64, XOR, rotation) to create layered transformations that resist brute-force decoding.</li>
</ul>

<p>This design allows DDR-based malware to persist even when individual endpoints are removed. Once one dead drop is taken down, the adversary can generate another using the same encoding methods. Reactive takedown strategies fail to scale. Our objective was to target the <em>techniques</em> rather than the <em>endpoints</em>.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/blogs/spycraft/ddr.jpg" alt="Illustrative dead drop resolver workflow" class="img-framed" width="70%" /></p>

<p class="figcaption">Razy’s DDR workflow. (1) The operator hides a manipulated C&amp;C address on X.com. (2) Razy fetches the dead drop after infection. (3) Layered decoding reveals the live C&amp;C rendezvous point.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="from-reactive-to-proactive-defense">From Reactive to Proactive Defense</h2>

<p>Existing defenses against DDR activity focus on removing individual dead drops that are currently active. Each removal is temporary. Malware authors reuse the same manipulation logic to encode new C&amp;C addresses, generating polymorphic variants faster than defenders can remove them.</p>

<p>Our research proposed a different approach that targets the decoding logic rather than the infrastructure. Each DDR malware sample contains the algorithms it uses to decode its hidden C&amp;C data. If those algorithms can be isolated and analyzed, they can be repurposed into <em>recipes</em> that allow analysts and web providers to automatically uncover new, similarly encoded content across their platforms.</p>

<p>This insight formed the basis for a proactive remediation method. Instead of reacting to visible infections, we analyze the malware’s de-manipulation behavior to extract its decoding process and use it to anticipate future activity.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="framework-from-localization-to-recipe-extraction">Framework: From Localization to Recipe Extraction</h2>

<p>We developed a systematic framework inspired by our research prototype <strong>VADER</strong> (<em>proactiVe deAd Drop rEsolver Remediation</em>). VADER analyzes malware binaries to uncover DDR behavior and derive reusable decoding recipes in three structured phases:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>DDR logic localization.</strong><br />
The malware is instrumented to monitor data flow from web fetches to C&amp;C communications. When content retrieved from a public web service later initiates a C&amp;C connection, those execution paths are isolated to confirm DDR functionality.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Boundary isolation.</strong><br />
Once the relevant regions are identified, execution is paused around them to extract precise input and output boundaries. These boundaries define where the malware begins and ends its de-manipulation routines, enabling accurate symbolic state capture.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Symbolic recipe identification.</strong><br />
From these symbolic states, mathematical expressions (λ) are extracted to describe each transformation applied to the fetched data. These expressions are compared against a reference library of known algorithms (e.g., Base64, XOR, Base16, character rotation, etc.) to recover the complete decoding sequence used by the malware.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><img src="/assets/blogs/spycraft/symbex.jpg" alt="Symbolic Expression Matching" class="img-framed" width="50%" /></p>

<p class="figcaption">VADER (1) injects symbolic data (λ) into the malware to localize DDR decoding logic and (2) generate a symbolic expression (Mλ). Reference decoder algorithms (e.g., Base16, XOR) are then symbolically executed using the same constraints to (3) produce comparable expressions (B16λ, XORλ). VADER first (4) performs structural matching between expressions, and if differences remain, uses a symbolic solver to evaluate their concrete outputs under identical constraints. A high ratio of matched paths (5) confirms that the malware routine and reference decoder are functionally equivalent.</p>

<p>This symbolic approach scales across malware families and isolates decoder logic with precision. Each specimen can be profiled automatically, the corresponding de-manipulation recipe extracted, and that recipe reused to locate dead drops before operators deploy malware.</p>

<h3 id="mudrop-case-study-proactive-dead-drop-discovery">Mudrop Case Study: Proactive Dead Drop Discovery</h3>

<p>The Mudrop case demonstrates how VADER transitions defenders from reactive response to proactive discovery. Once the symbolic de-manipulation recipe was recovered, we scanned WordPress posts, applied the recipe to decode them automatically, and identified three previously unknown dead drops prepared for use by the operator.</p>

<p class="figcaption"><img src="/assets/blogs/spycraft/mudrop.png" alt="Mudrop Proactive Discovery Placeholder" class="img-framed" width="70%" />
To overcome this challenge, VADER scans accessible WordPress posts or messages, decodes them using the de-manipulation recipe from Mudrop (Row 4), and extracts IPs or URLs via a regular expression. It then checks these against blocklists (e.g., VirusTotal, URLHaus) to classify web app accounts as dead drops for remediation. As this table shows, VADER proactively discovered three previously unknown WordPress dead drops-selfcut (Proactive Discovery 1), brainbot02 (Proactive Discovery 2), and suck4 (Proactive Discovery 3)-demonstrating its ability to detect varied content beyond direct matches.</p>

<p>The method generalizes across malware families. Even when two samples implement the same decoder differently (e.g., one as string operations, another as arithmetic transformations), symbolic comparison detects their shared logic. For complex, multi-stage decoders (e.g., Base16 followed by XOR and rotation), concolic execution and stepwise concretization reveal algorithmic boundaries, producing recipes accurate enough for automated detection.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="operational-impact">Operational Impact</h2>

<p>We applied VADER to large-scale malware analysis and live web data collection with measurable results:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Analyzed <strong>100,000</strong> Windows samples from <strong>2012–2022</strong>, identifying <strong>8,906</strong> DDR specimens.</li>
  <li>Discovered <strong>11</strong> web applications abused for DDR content. <strong>Pastebin</strong> accounted for <strong>68%</strong>, while <strong>blockchain explorers</strong> represented <strong>25%</strong> (23 transaction IDs, 14 wallet IDs).</li>
  <li>Extracted <strong>7</strong> unique de-manipulation recipes, dominated by <strong>Base64</strong> (<strong>40%</strong>) and hybrid sequences involving string parsing, XOR, Base16, and rotation.</li>
  <li>Collaborated with platform providers to remove <strong>88%</strong> of discovered dead drops, disrupting <strong>6,674</strong> malware samples and achieving a <strong>94.4%</strong> neutralization rate.</li>
  <li>Achieved a <strong>57%</strong> increase in DDR-related traffic visibility after integrating recipe-based detection.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="looking-ahead">Looking Ahead</h2>

<p>Dead Drop Resolvers represent a lasting evolution in adversarial strategy. By embedding hidden command infrastructure within trusted platforms, attackers exploit both platform trust and internet scalability. The challenge is not to find every endpoint but to identify the <em>patterns</em> that create them.</p>

<p>Our research shows that defenders can reuse the adversary’s decoding logic for advantage. By extracting symbolic recipes from malware, mapping them to known algorithms, and scanning proactively for those patterns, defenders can identify and remove malicious data before it becomes operational.</p>

<p>The full study, <strong><em>Enhanced Web Application Security Through Proactive Dead Drop Resolver Remediation</em></strong>, provides complete technical details, symbolic analysis methods, and collaborative results. This approach moves defense from chasing threats after compromise to dismantling the mechanisms that enable them.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="/publications/vader-dead-drop-resolver/">Publication summary and PDF</a></li>
</ul>

<p>Spycraft 2.0 may hide commands in plain sight, but with the right analysis pipeline, defenders can restore visibility and stay ahead of the next dead drop.</p>]]></content><author><name>Jonathan Fuller</name><email>hello@empiricaldefense.com</email></author><category term="posts" /><category term="talks" /><category term="malware" /><category term="command-and-control" /><category term="dead-drop-resolvers" /><category term="research" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Turning dead drop resolver tradecraft against botnet operators, as presented at BSidesNYC 0x05.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/blogs/spycraft/thumbnail.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/blogs/spycraft/thumbnail.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Enhanced Web Application Security Through Proactive Dead Drop Resolver Remediation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/vader-dead-drop-resolver/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Enhanced Web Application Security Through Proactive Dead Drop Resolver Remediation" /><published>2025-10-13T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-10-22T04:56:06-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/vader</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/vader-dead-drop-resolver/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Conference</strong>: 32nd ACM Conference on Computer and Communications Security (CCS), Taipei, Taiwan, 2025<br />
<strong>Authors</strong>: <u>Jonathan Fuller</u>*, M. Yao*, S. Agarwal, S. Barua, T. Hirani, A. K. Sikder, B. Saltaformaggio<br />
<strong>Acceptance Rate</strong>: 13.8%</p>

<h2 id="highlights">Highlights</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Detects and flags manipulated dead drops across seven popular web apps before attackers weaponize them.</li>
  <li>Automates layered de-manipulation, surfacing 57.1% more active C2 endpoints than signature-based tools.</li>
  <li>Delivers takedown intelligence that helped providers remove 13 hidden drop locations during evaluation.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="resources">Resources</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="/assets/papers/ccs25.pdf">PDF</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/CyFI-Lab-Public/VADER">Source code</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="abstract">Abstract</h2>

<p>Dead Drop Resolver (DDR) malware evades traditional Command and Control (C&amp;C) server takedowns by dynamically resolving C&amp;C addresses hosted on popular web applications, such as Dropbox and Pastebin. These addresses are often manipulated (i.e., encoded or encrypted), rendering existing detection techniques largely ineffective. To tackle this challenge, we introduce VADER, a malware forensics system specifically designed for the proactive detection of dead drops. Analyzing a dataset of 100k malware samples collected in the wild, VADER identified 8,906 DDR malware samples from 110 families that leverage 273 dead drops across seven web applications. Additionally, it proactively uncovered 57.1% more dead drops spanning 11 web applications. Case studies revealed that over 40% of DDR malware samples employ sophisticated, layered de-manipulation algorithms, highlighting the prevalence and complexity of this evasion technique. Beyond detection, VADER enabled proactive remediation by discovering 13 previously unknown dead drops from a single DDR malware sample. This approach empowers web application providers to systematically scan their platforms, enabling the early detection and mitigation of dead drops.</p>

<h2 id="artifact-badges">Artifact Badges</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Available</li>
  <li>Functional</li>
  <li>Reproduced</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="media-coverage">Media Coverage</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.deeptempo.ai/blogs/dead-drop-resolvers-malwares-quiet-rendezvous-and-why-adaptive-defense-matters">Deeptempo AI - Malware’s Quiet Rendezvous</a></li>
  <li><a href="hhttps://research.gatech.edu/hiding-plain-sight-disrupting-malwares-secret-web-dead-drops">Georgia Tech Research - Hiding in Plain Sight</a></li>
  <li><a href="hhttps://research.gatech.edu/hiding-plain-sight-disrupting-malwares-secret-web-dead-drops">The Hacker News - Weekly Recap</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="bibtex">BibTeX</h2>

<div class="language-bibtex highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nc">@inproceedings</span><span class="p">{</span><span class="nl">fuller2025vader</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">title</span>     <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{Enhanced Web Application Security Through Proactive Dead Drop Resolver Remediation}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">author</span>    <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{Fuller, Jonathan and Yao, Mingxuan and Agarwal, Saumya and Barua, Srimanta and Hirani, Taleb and Sikder, Amit K. and Saltaformaggio, Brendan}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">booktitle</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{Proceedings of the 32nd ACM Conference on Computer and Communications Security (CCS)}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">year</span>      <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{2025}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">address</span>   <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{Taipei, Taiwan}</span><span class="p">,</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name>Jonathan Fuller</name><email>hello@empiricaldefense.com</email></author><category term="publications" /><category term="malware" /><category term="command-and-control" /><category term="dead drops" /><category term="web-security" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Proactive detection and remediation of Dead Drop Resolver malware on web applications, accepted to ACM CCS 2025 (13.8% acceptance rate).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Operationalizing Zero Trust: CECOM SEC and West Point Collaborate</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/operationalizing-zero-trust/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Operationalizing Zero Trust: CECOM SEC and West Point Collaborate" /><published>2025-09-11T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-10-22T04:56:06-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/operationalizing-zero-trust</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/operationalizing-zero-trust/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Venue</strong>: U.S. Army<br />
<strong>Authors</strong>: F. Shah, <u>Jonathan Fuller</u><br />
<strong>Date</strong>: September 11, 2025</p>

<h2 id="highlights">Highlights</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Details the first practical evaluation of the SEC-developed mapping between Zero Trust principles and the DoD Risk Management Framework.</li>
  <li>Shares insights from the joint U.S. Army CECOM Software Engineering Center and West Point collaboration on adoption challenges.</li>
  <li>Captures feedback loops needed to operationalize Zero Trust across Army systems and accreditation processes.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="resources">Resources</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.army.mil/article/288418">Official article</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="abstract">Abstract</h2>

<p>The Communications-Electronics Command Software Engineering Center and the U.S. Military Academy at West Point partnered to test the feasibility of the SEC-developed mapping between Zero Trust and the Department of Defense Risk Management Framework. This effort marked the first practical exercise to gather feedback on the mapping’s application and to identify adjustments needed to operationalize Zero Trust within Army environments.</p>

<h2 id="media-coverage">Media Coverage</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.executivegov.com/articles/army-zero-trust-mapping-cecom-sec-west-point">Army Operationalizes Zero Trust</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Jonathan Fuller</name><email>hello@empiricaldefense.com</email></author><category term="publications" /><category term="zero-trust" /><category term="DoW" /><category term="risk-management" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Field collaboration between CECOM SEC and West Point to validate Zero Trust mappings to the DoD Risk Management Framework.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">CS483 Digital Forensics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/teaching/2025-01-15-cs483-digital-forensics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CS483 Digital Forensics" /><published>2025-01-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-10-21T22:07:32-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/teaching/cs483-digital-forensics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/teaching/2025-01-15-cs483-digital-forensics/"><![CDATA[<p>CS483 Digital Forensics explores the evidence left behind when malicious activity occurs on an information system. Students build on earlier work in operating systems, file formats, file system structures, computer architecture, and networking to perform disciplined investigations.</p>

<p><strong>Institution:</strong> United States Military Academy<br />
<strong>Department:</strong> Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science<br />
<strong>Location:</strong> West Point, NY<br />
<strong>Role:</strong> Course Director<br />
<strong>Term:</strong> Spring 2025</p>

<p>The course begins with a guided review of foundational concepts, then advances into locating and extracting digital evidence. Students tackle three self-directed projects and multiple in-class challenges that require them to apply forensic techniques, communicate findings, and articulate mitigation strategies.</p>

<h3 id="learning-objectives">Learning Objectives</h3>

<p>Upon successful completion, students are able to:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Apply a scientific methodology to the acquisition and analysis of digital evidence.</li>
  <li>Use multiple software tools to acquire and analyze digital evidence.</li>
  <li>Explain digital forensics concepts, results, and conclusions to both technical and non-technical audiences.</li>
  <li>Demonstrate an understanding of the processes and tooling required to reverse engineer malware.</li>
  <li>Perform memory forensics to hunt for adversary and criminal activity.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Jonathan Fuller</name><email>hello@empiricaldefense.com</email></author><category term="teaching" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Undergraduate course examining how to recover and analyze evidence after malicious activity on information systems.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">CS483: Digital Forensics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/teaching/2024-01-15-cs483-digital-forensics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CS483: Digital Forensics" /><published>2024-01-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-10-21T22:07:32-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/teaching/cs483-digital-forensics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/teaching/2024-01-15-cs483-digital-forensics/"><![CDATA[<p>CS483 Digital Forensics introduces students to the evidence left behind when malicious activity occurs on an information system. Building on operating systems, file formats, file system structures, computer architecture, and networking, they practice disciplined investigations across end hosts and enterprise environments.</p>

<p><strong>Institution:</strong> United States Military Academy<br />
<strong>Department:</strong> Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science<br />
<strong>Location:</strong> West Point, NY<br />
<strong>Role:</strong> Course Director<br />
<strong>Term:</strong> Spring 2024</p>

<p>Throughout the semester students complete three self-directed projects and a series of in-class challenges that require them to acquire data, interpret artifacts, and communicate findings to technical and non-technical audiences. The capstone focus is on applying science-based methodologies across host-based forensics, malware triage, and memory analysis to detect and disrupt adversary activity.</p>]]></content><author><name>Jonathan Fuller</name><email>hello@empiricaldefense.com</email></author><category term="teaching" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Undergraduate course examining how to recover and analyze digital evidence after malicious activity on information systems.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">COP 630 Cyber Law and Digital Forensics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/teaching/2023-10-01-cyber-law-digital-forensics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COP 630 Cyber Law and Digital Forensics" /><published>2023-10-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-10-22T09:32:07-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/teaching/cyber-law-digital-forensics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/teaching/2023-10-01-cyber-law-digital-forensics/"><![CDATA[<p>COP 630 Cyber Law and Digital Forensics examines the U.S. and international legal frameworks that govern cyber operations and the collection of digital evidence. The course builds on COP 620 and blends legal analysis with hands-on forensic practice in a virtual lab environment.</p>

<p><strong>Institution:</strong> University of Maryland Global Campus<br />
<strong>Department:</strong> School of Cybersecurity and Information Technology<br />
<strong>Location:</strong> Virtual<br />
<strong>Role:</strong> Course Instructor<br />
<strong>Term:</strong> Fall 2023<br />
<strong>Credits:</strong> 6</p>

<p>Students explore three interlocking modules:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Legal Frameworks.</strong> Study U.S. statutory and case law, international norms, and rules of engagement that shape cyber operations.</li>
  <li><strong>Operational Compliance.</strong> Design and defend a cyber-offense campaign that remains compliant with U.S. regulations and policy constraints.</li>
  <li><strong>Applied Digital Forensics.</strong> Use industry tools to acquire and analyse evidence from network captures, storage media, and RAM across common operating systems and devices.</li>
</ol>

<p>Throughout the term, learners execute labs in a virtualized environment, document chain of custody, and deliver expert-witness style reports tying technical findings back to legal requirements.</p>]]></content><author><name>Jonathan Fuller</name><email>hello@empiricaldefense.com</email></author><category term="teaching" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Graduate-level exploration of cyber law and applied digital forensics, delivered in a virtual environment.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Invited Tutorial: Counteracting Web Application Abuse in Malware</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/secdev-tutorial-web-application-abuse/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Invited Tutorial: Counteracting Web Application Abuse in Malware" /><published>2023-09-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-10-22T09:32:07-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/secdev-tutorial-marsea</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/secdev-tutorial-web-application-abuse/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Conference</strong>: 2023 IEEE Secure Development Conference (SecDev): Invited Tutorial<br />
<strong>Authors</strong>: M. Yao, <u>Jonathan Fuller</u>, R. Pai Sridhar, S. Agarwal, A. K. Sikder, B. Saltaformaggio</p>

<h2 id="highlights">Highlights</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Distills forensic best practices for identifying and containing Web App-Engaged malware across popular web platforms.</li>
  <li>Showcases the Marsea pipeline, enabling responders to document proof-of-abuse and coordinate takedowns with service providers.</li>
  <li>Features a 90-minute mix of tool walkthroughs and labs, giving participants practical experience handling WAE incidents end-to-end.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="resources">Resources</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="">PDF</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/CyFI-Lab-Public/MARSEA">Source code</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="abstract">Abstract</h2>

<p>Web applications offer a broad range of functionalities that are exploited by malware to serve as alternatives to traditional attacker-controlled servers. To effectively combat these Web App-Engaged (WAE) malware, prompt coordination between incident responders and web application providers is crucial. Any delay in this collaboration can allow WAE malware to flourish, posing serious security risks to the compromised web applications.</p>

<p>Our tutorial is designed to enlighten attendees on the best practices for forensic analysis of malware, while also helping to assess the scope of infection caused by WAE malware. Additionally, we will discuss the essential “proof-of-abuse” documentation required to facilitate groundbreaking collaboration between incident responders and service providers.</p>

<p>To enhance the security awareness of incident responders and to streamline forensic analysis for quicker response times, we are offering a 90-minute tutorial. This educational session will address the unique challenges posed by WAE malware and explore specialized remediation techniques available through web application platforms. We will also unveil a recently-developed forensic tool designed specifically for handling WAE malware. The tutorial will be a hybrid experience, featuring both a walkthrough of this innovative tool and a hands-on exercise, enabling participants to use the tool for analyzing WAE malware effectively.</p>

<h2 id="bibtex">BibTeX</h2>

<div class="language-bibtex highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nc">@inproceedings</span><span class="p">{</span><span class="nl">yao2023secdevtutorial</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">title</span>     <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{Invited Tutorial: Counteracting Web Application Abuse in Malware}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">author</span>    <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{Yao, Mingxuan and Fuller, Jonathan and Pai Sridhar, Ranjita and Agarwal, Saumya and Sikder, Amit K. and Saltaformaggio, Brendan}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">booktitle</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{Proceedings of the IEEE Secure Development Conference (SecDev)}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">year</span>      <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{2023}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">note</span>      <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{Invited Tutorial}</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name>Jonathan Fuller</name><email>hello@empiricaldefense.com</email></author><category term="publications" /><category term="malware" /><category term="incident-response" /><category term="tutorials" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hands-on SecDev 2023 tutorial that teaches incident responders how to triage and remediate Web App-Engaged malware using the Marsea toolchain.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hiding in Plain Sight: An Empirical Study of Web Application Abuse in Malware</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/marsea-web-application-abuse/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hiding in Plain Sight: An Empirical Study of Web Application Abuse in Malware" /><published>2023-08-09T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-10-22T04:56:06-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/marsea</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/marsea-web-application-abuse/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Conference</strong>: 32nd USENIX Security Symposium (USENIX Security), Anaheim, CA, 2023<br />
<strong>Authors</strong>: M. Yao, <u>Jonathan Fuller</u>, R. Pai Kasturi, S. Agarwal, A. K. Sikder, B. Saltaformaggio<br />
<strong>Acceptance Rate</strong>: 29.2%</p>

<h2 id="highlights">Highlights</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Identifies 893 web-application-engaged malware specimens across 97 families abusing 29 popular web applications.</li>
  <li>Measures a 226% surge in WAE malware since 2020 while observing a 13.7% drop in reliance on attacker-controlled servers.</li>
  <li>Delivers the Marsea pipeline, enabling responders and providers to remove over 50% of malicious web content encountered.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="resources">Resources</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="/assets/papers/sec23yao.pdf">PDF</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.usenix.org/system/files/sec23_slides_yao-mingxuan.pdf">Slides</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o0SWc0cwqy4">Talk recording</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/CyFI-Lab-Public/MARSEA">Source code</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="abstract">Abstract</h2>

<p>Web applications provide a wide array of utilities that are abused by malware as a replacement for traditional attacker-controlled servers. Thwarting these Web App-Engaged (WAE) malware requires rapid collaboration between incident responders and web app providers. Unfortunately, our research found that delays in this collaboration allow WAE malware to thrive. We developed Marsea, an automated malware analysis pipeline that studies WAE malware and enables rapid remediation. Given 10K malware samples, Marsea revealed 893 WAE malware in 97 families abusing 29 web apps. Our research uncovered a 226% increase in the number of WAE malware since 2020 and that malware authors are beginning to reduce their reliance on attacker-controlled servers. In fact, we found a 13.7% decrease in WAE malware relying on attacker-controlled servers. To date, we have used Marsea to collaborate with the web app providers to take down 50% of the malicious web app content.</p>

<h2 id="artifact-badges">Artifact Badges</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Available</li>
  <li>Functional</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="honors">Honors</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Invited tutorial at the 2023 IEEE Secure Development Conference (SecDev).</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="media-coverage">Media Coverage</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://research.gatech.edu/playing-hide-and-seek-new-breed-malware-threatening-millions-users">Georgia Tech - Playing Hide and seek with Malware</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://techxplore.com/news/2023-09-playing-malware-threatening-millions-users.html">TechXPlore - New Breed of Malware</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.techtimes.com/articles/296248/20230912/researchers-find-new-breed-malware-hiding-dropbox-discord.htm">TechTimes - Malware Hiding in Dropbox, Discord</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.ilsoftware.it/web-app-engaged-i-malware-che-si-nascondono-in-dropbox-e-discord/">ILSoftware - Wep-App Engagnge Malware</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="bibtex">BibTeX</h2>

<div class="language-bibtex highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nc">@inproceedings</span><span class="p">{</span><span class="nl">yao2023marsea</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">title</span>     <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{Hiding in Plain Sight: An Empirical Study of Web Application Abuse in Malware}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">author</span>    <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{Yao, Meng and Fuller, Jonathan and Pai Kasturi, Ranjita and Agarwal, Saumya and Sikder, Amit K. and Saltaformaggio, Brendan}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">booktitle</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{Proceedings of the 32nd USENIX Security Symposium (USENIX Security)}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">year</span>      <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{2023}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">address</span>   <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{Anaheim, CA}</span><span class="p">,</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name>Jonathan Fuller</name><email>hello@empiricaldefense.com</email></author><category term="publications" /><category term="malware" /><category term="web-applications" /><category term="incident-response" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Large-scale analysis of web-application-engaged malware and the Marsea remediation pipeline, accepted to USENIX Security 2023 (29.2% acceptance rate).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploiting Malware Communication Protocols for Command-and-Control Server Infiltration</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/the-byte-c2-infiltration/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploiting Malware Communication Protocols for Command-and-Control Server Infiltration" /><published>2023-05-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-10-22T09:32:07-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/the-byte-infiltration</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/the-byte-c2-infiltration/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Venue</strong>: The Byte<br />
<strong>Author</strong>: <u>Jonathan Fuller</u><br />
<strong>Date</strong>: May 1, 2023</p>

<h2 id="highlights">Highlights</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Explores how malware communication protocol weaknesses enable covert infiltration of command-and-control infrastructure.</li>
  <li>Shares operational guidance for cyber operators confronting adversary C2 networks in the field.</li>
  <li>Bridges research findings with practitioner insights for the 780th Military Intelligence Brigade (Cyber).</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="resources">Resources</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="/assets/papers/thebyte23.pdf">PDF</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="abstract">Abstract</h2>

<p>This article outlines methods for exploiting malware communication protocols to gain footholds inside adversary command-and-control servers. By analyzing protocol manipulation opportunities and applying lessons from battlefield operations, it demonstrates how defenders can turn the tables on malware operators to enable covert monitoring and disrupt hostile infrastructure.</p>]]></content><author><name>Jonathan Fuller</name><email>hello@empiricaldefense.com</email></author><category term="publications" /><category term="command-and-control" /><category term="forensics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Article in The Byte detailing practical techniques for infiltrating C2 infrastructure by abusing malware communication protocols.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mistrust Plugins You Must: A Large-Scale Study Of Malicious Plugins In WordPress Marketplaces</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/yoda-malicious-wordpress-plugins/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mistrust Plugins You Must: A Large-Scale Study Of Malicious Plugins In WordPress Marketplaces" /><published>2022-04-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-10-22T04:56:06-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/yoda</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/yoda-malicious-wordpress-plugins/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Conference</strong>: 31st USENIX Security Symposium (USENIX Security), Boston, MA, 2022<br />
<strong>Authors</strong>: R. Pai Kasturi, <u>Jonathan Fuller</u>, Y. Sun, O. Chabklo, A. Rodriguez, J. Park, B. Saltaformaggio<br />
<strong>Acceptance Rate</strong>: 18.1%</p>

<h2 id="highlights">Highlights</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Analyzes 400K production web servers dating back to 2012 to uncover malicious plugin campaigns.</li>
  <li>Introduces YODA, an automated framework that identifies and traces malicious plugin origins across marketplaces, piracy sites, and post-deployment compromises.</li>
  <li>Documents $41.5K spent on malicious marketplace plugins, $228K in lost revenue from pirated plugins, and $834K in post-deployment compromises, with 94% of malicious plugins still active.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="resources">Resources</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="/assets/papers/sec22.pdf">PDF</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://youtu.be/16FmkoX_ZMY">Talk recording</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://youtu.be/TUATgmVKdf8">Demo</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/CyFI-Lab-Public/YODA">Source code</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="abstract">Abstract</h2>

<p>Modern websites owe most of their aesthetics and functionalities to Content Management Systems (CMS) plugins, which are bought and sold on widely popular marketplaces. Driven by economic incentives, attackers abuse the trust in this economy: selling malware on legitimate marketplaces, pirating popular plugins, and infecting plugins post-deployment. This research studied the evolution of CMS plugins in over 400K production webservers dating back to 2012. We developed YODA, an automated framework to detect malicious plugins and track down their origin. YODA uncovered 47,337 malicious plugins on 24,931 unique websites. Among these, $41.5K had been spent on 3,685 malicious plugins sold on legitimate plugin marketplaces. Pirated plugins cheated developers out of $228K in revenues. Post-deployment attacks infected $834K worth of previously benign plugins with malware. Lastly, YODA informs our remediation efforts, as over 94% of these malicious plugins are still active today.</p>

<h2 id="honors">Honors</h2>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>CSAW’22 Applied Research Competition Award Finalist</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Invited for a USENIX ;login: Magazine article</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="media-coverage">Media Coverage</h2>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://cacm.acm.org/news/locking-down-secure-open-source-software/">Locking Down Secure Open Source Software</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://thehackernews.com/2022/06/yoda-tool-found-47000-malicious.html">YODA Tool Found ~47,000 Malicious WordPress Plugins Installed in Over 24,000 Sites</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://siliconangle.com/2022/08/29/researchers-find-malicious-plugins-25000-wordpress-sites/">Researchers find malicious plugins on 25,000 WordPress sites</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.cc.gatech.edu/news/eight-year-study-shows-dark-side-wordpress-plugins">Eight-Year Study Shows the Dark Side of WordPress Plugins</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.usenix.org/publications/loginonline/mistrust-plugins-you-must-large-scale-study-malicious-plugins-wordpress">USENIX ;login: Mistrust Plugins You Must</a></p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="bibtex">BibTeX</h2>

<div class="language-bibtex highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nc">@inproceedings</span><span class="p">{</span><span class="nl">kasturi2022yoda</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">title</span>     <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{Mistrust Plugins You Must: A Large-Scale Study Of Malicious Plugins In WordPress Marketplaces}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">author</span>    <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{Pai Kasturi, Ranjita and Fuller, Jonathan and Sun, Yiting and Chabklo, Omar and Rodriguez, Andres and Park, Jeman and Saltaformaggio, Brendan}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">booktitle</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{Proceedings of the 31st USENIX Security Symposium (USENIX Security)}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">year</span>      <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{2022}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">address</span>   <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{Boston, MA}</span><span class="p">,</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name>Jonathan Fuller</name><email>hello@empiricaldefense.com</email></author><category term="publications" /><category term="malware" /><category term="wordpress" /><category term="content-management" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Measurement study of malicious WordPress plugins and the YODA detection pipeline, accepted to USENIX Security 2022 (18.1% acceptance rate).]]></summary></entry></feed>